What you&#39;ve done as you go through life is made choices.
Điều bạn làm khi còn sống là đưa ra các lựa chọn
You’ve chosen to go to university or not, to get married or not, have kids or not, travel or not.
Bạn chọn đi học đại học hoặc không, làm đám cưới hoặc không, có con hoặc không, đi du lịch hoặc không
You have made lifestyle choices, to smoke or not, exercise or not.
Bạn đưa ra các lựa chọn lối sống, hút thuốc hoặc không, tập thể dục hoặc không
You&#39;ve had good and bad things happen to you, maybe a car accident, maybe the experience
Bạn đã gặp chuyện tốt và xấu, ví dụ như bị tai nạn xe cộ hay thành công trong sự nghiệp
of great success in a career.
of great success in a career.
So by the time you get to be 80 and you&#39;ve made all these unique choices and had a variety
Nên đến khi 80 tuổi bạn đã đưa ra những lựa chọn riêng và nhiều điều đã xảy ra với bản
of things happen to you, then your persona, your brain, your personality, your social
khiến cho bản thân bạn, não, tính cách,và mối quan hệ của bạn đêu trở nên đặc biệt
networks, everything, is quite unique.
networks, everything, is quite unique.
That&#39;s why in the realm of, say, statistics or personality, older adult populations have
Đó là vì sao về mặt dữ liệu thống kê hay tính cách thì người lớn tuổi có độ lệch chuẩn lớn hơn
a greater standard deviation.
a greater standard deviation.
There is no such thing as a typical 70 year old.
Không có một mẫu người 70 tuổi cố định
So with increasing age, people get more and more different from each other.
Càng già thì con người ta càng khác nhau
We say there is increased heterogeneity with increasing age.
Có thể nói sự khác biệt tăng cùng với tuổi tác
And this is the second key gerontology principle.
Và đây là điểm chính thứ hai của lão khao học
For this reason older adults are a great population to study because there&#39;s a lot of variance
Vì lý do này mà người lớn tuổi là đối tượng nghiên cứu phần lớn bời vì có rất nhiều sự khác biệt
in the population.
in the population.
This is why if you gave a test to a room full of 30 year olds and a room full of 80 year
Đó là vì sao nếu bạn cùng khảo sát một phòng đầy người 30 tuổi và một phòng 80 tuổi
olds, the 80 year olds would have a much wider range of responses, whether you gave them
thì những người 80 tuổi sẽ có câu trả lời đa dạng hơn dù bạn có cho kiểm tra trí nhớ
a memory test, or personality test, or even just asked what&#39;s your favourite flavour of
hay tính cách, hay hỏi về vị kem yêu thích
ice cream.
ice cream.
Time and experience add up to heterogeneity.
Thời gian và kinh nghiệm góp phần vào sự khác biệt